A Guide to the Hilda Yates Warden Papers, 1959-2005
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
Hilda Yates Warden Papers 1959-2005
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
M 376
Two linear feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was a gift to Special Collections and Archives from Hilda Y. Warden in December 2007.
Custodial History
Special Collections and Archives has a signed Deed of Gift as of January 2008.
Biographical Information
Hilda Yates Warden was born and raised in Richmond, Virginia. She attended public schools in Richmond, graduating from Armstrong High School in 1931. She attended Virginia Union University (VUU), and while there was one of the founding members of the Beta Epsilon chapter of Delta Sigma Theta Sorority. She graduated in 1935 with a degree in chemistry at the age of 17.
After graduation, Warden taught school in a one-room schoolhouse near Roanoke. In 1941 she married George Warden, Sr., and with him had two sons, who they raised in Richmond Virginia. By 1950, Warden was working for the Richmond Department of Welfare at a time when African Americans were just beginning to be hired as supervisors in the department. Warden realized that she needed to further her education to be promoted into a supervisory position, and decided to start by taking one class in social work.
Warden wished to apply to Richmond Professional Institute (RPI, later VCU) but was barred because the administration at RPI had not made a decision on whether to admit African Americans. Eventually RPI allowed Warden to apply. However, while white working students were allowed to attend the school part-time, Warden and other African Americans wishing to attend would be required to attend classes full-time, meaning they would have to quit their jobs. Warden decided to apply despite this condition, and in 1951, she was quietly admitted to the school of Social Work at RPI along with four other African American students. She went on to receive her Master's of Science degree in Rehabilitation Counseling from RPI in 1954.
After receiving her MS, Warden was hired at Virginia Union University as a counselor where she worked for eleven years. While there, she directed several federal programs. Once leaving VUU, Warden worked at the Richmond Department for Aging from 1976 to 1983. She held positions with the Richmond Committee of Black Social Workers, Offender Aid and Restoration, and the Virginia Commission on Human Relations. She was also active in the Richmond Committee of Black Social Workers.
In 1984, Warden began working as a legislative assistant to Senator Yvonne Miller, retiring from her staff in 2011. Warden was a lifetime member of the NAACP. She received many awards during her lifetime for her dedication and service to her profession, including from the YWCA of Richmond and the City of Richmond. Hilda Yates Warden passed away in Richmond, Virginia on August 29, 2015 at the age of 97.
Scope and Content
The collection includes minutes, correspondence, reports, newspaper clippings, publications and other materials related to Warden's interests in civil rights and prisoner treatment. The materials date from the mid-1960s until the mid-2000s, with the bulk of the collection dating from 1969-1971. A significant portion of the collection is comprised of materials from her activities within the Virginia Commission on Human Relations, Richmond Y.W.C.A., and Offender Aid and Restoration. The collection also contains some items related to her husband George Warden's work at the Manhattan For Hire Car Corporation.
Arrangement
Collection is in alphabetical order. Boxes 2-4 are oversized.
Contents List
- Benedict College, The Tiger Spirit 1969 (Box-folder 1:1)
- Committee of Black Social Workers 1970 (Box-folder 1:2)
- Economic Education Bulletin 1967 (Box-folder 1:3)
- Home Mission Board, Southern Baptist Convention undated (Box-folder 1:4)
- Manhattan For Hire Car Corporation, 1969 undated (Box-folder 1:5)
- The Metropolitan Observer 1970-1971 (Box-folder 1:6)
- Human Relation Committee Newsletters 1980-1981 (Box-folder 1:7)
- National Gay Task Force undated (Box-folder 1:8)
- Offender Aid and Restoration 1970-1971, undated (Box-folder 1:9)
- Richmond Y.W.C.A. 1968 (Box-folder 1:10)
- The Tenant Progress 1987 (Box-folder 1:11)
- Toastmaster 1969-1970 (Box-folder 1:12)
- USC Trojan Family 1970 (Box-folder 1:13)
- Virginia Commission on Human Relations (1 of 3) 1964-1968, undated (Box-folder 1:14)
- Virginia Commission on Human Relations (2 of 3) 1970-1972, 1975-1980 (Box-folder 1:15)
- Virginia Commission on Human Relations (3 of 3) 1981-1982 (Box-folder 1:16)
- Virginia Union University 1970-1971, undated (Box-folder 1:17)
- Virginia Union University, The Panther 1971 (Box-folder 1:18)
- Westwood Baptist Church Men's Day Program undated (Box-folder 1:19)
- Berkley Barb 1969 (Box-folder 2:1)
- The Black Panther 1969-1970 (Box-folder 2:2)
- Changing Times 1969-1970 (Box-folder 2:3)
- Contact 1969-1970 (Box-folder 2:4)
- Ebony Magazine 1969-1970 (Box-folder 2:5)
- Government Publications 1959, 1967, 1975, 1977, undated (Box-folder 3:1)
- The Guidepost 1970 (Box-folder 3:2)
- Jet Magazine 1969-1970 (Box-folder 3:3)
- Newspaper Clippings 1970-1971, 1978, 1980, 1982 (Box-folder 3:4)
- Periodicals 1969-1970 (Box-folder 3:5)
- The Plain Truth 1970 (Box-folder 3:6)
- Richmond Afro-American 1970-1971 (Box-folder 4:1)
- Richmond Afro-American Clippings 1980-1981 (Box-folder 4:2)
- The Richmond News Leader 1970-1972, 1977-1979, 1981-1984 (Box-folder 4:3)
- The Richmond Times-Dispatch 1969-1970, 1977-1983, 2005 (Box-folder 4:4)
- San Francisco's Dock of the Bay undated (Box-folder 4:5)
- Unidentified Clippings 1970, 1978, 1982-1983, undated (Box-folder 4:6)